Finding Aid for Milton Kemnitz Papers, 1932-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Milton Kemnitz Papers 1932-1995, 1960-1990
Kemnitz, Milton.
3 linear feet
9427 Aa 2
Ann Arbor-based artist specializing in images of local businesses and sites. The collection has been arranged in three series. The Artwork series includes drawings of buildings and other projects, publications containing reproductions of his work, and files relating to galleries, exhibits, auctions, and art fairs. The Supplemental Materials series concerns the art organizations and associations of which Kemnitz was a member, correspondence, and files pertaining to other activities, notably the Bird Hills Park controversy. The third series, Southern White Migration to Detroit in the 1930s, consists of research materials and reports resulting from Kemnitz' research as a member of a University of Michigan sociology seminar on metropolitan community organization. A portion includes Elmer Akers' research on the Black Legion.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Milton and Eddie Kemnitz Donor # 8234 beginning in 1994.
The papers are open to research.
Milton Kemnitz is one of Ann Arbor's best known artists. His drawings and paintings all have a unique, identifiable style and have been widely reproduced -- on greeting cards, shopping bags, calendars and magazine covers. His work also appears on the walls of the city -- both inside and outside. In 1974 the mayor of Ann Arbor recognized his contributions and declared a "Milt Kemnitz Day."
Kemnitz was born in Detroit, Michigan and graduated from the University of Michigan with a degree from the College of Literature, Arts and Sciences, in 1933. During World War II he served as a merchant seaman, and started to paint on a stint to the Mediterranean. Once the war was over, he returned to Ann Arbor, and together with his wife and collaborator Eddie, whom he married in 1939, has made the city his home ever since.
His work has been shown in numerous group and one-man shows, mainly in galleries in his home state. The Forsythe Gallery in Ann Arbor represented him for decades, and he has had connections with many other galleries over the years. His work is in the collections of many museums, institutions and corporations. He has published several books of drawings: Old West Side, Michigan Memories (1965), Ann Arbor Now and Then (1972)and London and Back (1977). Eddie helped him design and edit the books, a role she often filled in conjunction with Milt's larger projects.
Kemnitz did many commissioned pieces, especially drawings of buildings for individuals and corporations. In addition to these commissions, he often donated artwork or his expertise to support local activities. For instance, he sat on the Ann Arbor Sesquicentennial Committee and designed the commemorative silver bar, did lettering and drawings for the "Y" for over a decade, and helped keep The Ark, a local performance space, open.
In addition to supporting the arts in Ann Arbor, an effort that included membership in the Ann Arbor Art Association and numerous other organizations, Eddie and Milt were involved in other local causes. The biggest effort was to "Save Bird Hills Park" in 1971. This was a grassroots effort to fight the building of luxury condominiums on what had been parkland. The city agreed to buy the land from the developer and leave it as parkland if the people of Ann Arbor could raise one-fourth of the purchase price. 1500 people pledged a total of $90,000 but the developer still got the land.
His involvement with local organizations includes over fifty years of membership in the First Unitarian Universalist Church. Naturally, he did quite a bit of work for them over the years. In addition to his drawing of the church, which was used on programs and stationary for years, he experimented with a new medium and created a memorial stained glass window dedicated to Edward H. Redman, who had been minister from 1943 to 1960.
The papers of Milt Kemnitz have been divided into three series. The first series, ARTWORK, focuses on the artwork itself, and its reproduction and dissemination. This includes the following subseries: Drawings of Buildings, Other Projects, Publications and Galleries, Exhibits, Auctions & Art Fairs. The second series, called SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIALS, has three subseries, Art Organizations & Associations, Correspondence and Miscellaneous Personal Material. Much of this material concerns his career as an artist but relates less directly to the actual artwork than the material in the first series. The third series, SOUTHERN WHITE MIGRATION TO DETROIT IN THE 1930s, consists of research materials and reports resulting from Kemnitz' research as a member of a University of Michigan sociology seminar on metropolitan community organization.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Artists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Bird Hills Park (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Black Legion.; Kemnitz, Eddie.; Kemnitz, Milton.; Real estate development--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Rural-urban migration--Southern States.; Rural-urban migration--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Kemnitz, Milton.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Kemnitz, Eddie.; Akers, Elmer, 1899-
Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Prints.; Photographs.
- Artwork
  Within the ARTWORK series, Drawings of Buildings includes drawings of private residences and well known public buildings, mainly in Ann Arbor. These folders contain sketches on tracing paper, photographs of the actual houses and reproductions of the final drawings. Many of the drawings of buildings were used as greeting card art. Kemnitz excelled at depicting buildings, typically as line drawings but sometimes as paintings. Other Projects are larger in scope, encompassing work Kemnitz did that may include, but are not limited to, the drawing of a building. Commissioned works have not been separated from gifts by the artist, for it is not always clear into which category a work falls. Publications includes the books Kemnitz published and the various magazine covers and articles reproducing his work. Please see the clippings folders in the SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIALS series for potentially relevant newspaper articles. Galleries, Exhibits, Auctions & Art Fairs includes information about the various art events Kemnitz participated in.
  - Drawings of Buildings
    - Ann Arbor Bedding Company, 1001 Broadway (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Farmers Market (Box 1)
    - Home of Mary Beckerman, 901 Forest (Box 1)
    - Bishop and Shelton, 709 W. Huron (Box 1)
    - Home of Jack and Mary Ann Brown (Box 1)
    - Burns Park School (Box 1)
    - Caldwell & Reinhart Company, Realtors (Box 1)
    - Darrell Campbell, Hill and Geddes, Ann Arbor (Box 1)
    - Campus Smoke Shop (Box 1)
    - Canoe Livery (Box 1)
    - Christian Reformed Campus Chapel 1990 (Box 1)
    - Home of Don Cleveland, 628 South 1st. St., Ann Arbor 1987 (Box 1)
    - The Cottage (Box 1)
    - Cousins Heritage Inn, Dexter 1993 (Box 1)
    - The Depot, Ann Arbor (Box 1)
    - Home of Mary Dunham, 2756 Lowell 1991 (Box 1)
    - Home of Bill and Jane Ferguson, 1935 Cambridge Rd. 1988 (Box 1)
    - First Baptist Church 1983 (Box 1)
    - Home of Peter Heydon 1988 (Box 1)
    - Hilldene Apartments, Washtenaw Ave., Ann Arbor 1975 (Box 1)
    - Huron Valley Swim Club 1988 (Box 1)
    - Home of Abe Kadushin (Box 1)
    - Kahn Log Cabin, Jackie Miller, 1824 Arbordale (Box 1)
    - Kempf House, ca. 1986 (Box 1)
    - Kerrytown (Box 1)
    - Home of John and Peggy Laird (Box 1)
    - Home of Dick and Jackie Lewis 1990 (Box 1)
    - Lutheran Church of the Reformation 1974 (Box 1)
    - Home of Tom McEeachern, Harvard Place (Box 1)
    - Martha's house, S. Normal, Ypsilanti 1995 (Box 1)
    - Home of Bill Martin, "Glenwood" (Box 1)
    - Michigan Municipal League 1988 (Box 1)
    - Nickels Arcade (Box 1)
    - Old Firehouse (Box 1)
    - Packard Community Clinic 1978-1981 (Box 1)
    - Home of Mary Porter, 724 Oxford, Ann Arbor 1988 (Box 1)
    - Home of Jim and Tony Reese, 2009 Vinewood 1995 (Box 1)
    - Summit Medical Center, Inc. 1973 (Box 1)
    - University Elementary School (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan
      - Miscellaneous buildings (Box 1)
      - Power Center for the Performing Arts, ca. 1973 (Box 1)
      - President's House (ca. 1876) 1979 (Box 1)
      - Residence Halls 1984 (Box 1)
      - School of Business Administration (Box 1)
      - School of Law (Box 1)
    - Women's City Club 1986 (Box 1)
  - Other Projects
    - Ads featuring Kemnitz artwork (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Antique Fair & Sale, booklet cover 1972 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Art Fair, drawings and sketches 1965 (Box 1)
    - "Ann Arbor Observer 10th Anniversary Commemorative Calendar," painting by Kemnitz 1986 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Sesquicentennial Commission
      - Correspondence 1972-1975 (Box 1)
      - Meeting Minutes 1972-1973 (Box 1)
      - Papers 1973 (Box 1)
      - Sketches for commemorative silver bar designed by Kemnitz 1973 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor "Y"
      - Pictures and tracings of the old "Y" 1969-1985 (Box 1)
      - Pictures and tracings of the new "Y" 1975-1991 (Box 1)
      - Catalog covers 1981-1991 (Box 1)
      - Catalog drawings and lettering (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1979-1991 (Box 1)
    - The Ark 1975-1986 (Box 1)
    - Cleary College 1989 (Box 1)
    - Ecology Center greeting card designs 1981-1990 (Box 1)
    - "Eventful Ann Arbor: A Calendar by The Junior Service League of Ann Arbor," drawings by Kemnitz 1986 (Box 1)
    - First Unitarian Universalist Church
      - Drawings and other materials 1944-1990, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Stained glass 1986 (Box 1)
    - Great Lakes Federal Savings, drawing of a 1908 Brush automobile (Box 1)
    - Greeting cards drawn by Kemnitz (Box 1)
    - "Michigan: A Bicentennial Calendar," drawings by Kemnitz 1976 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous artwork by Kemnitz, photographed, some with the artist (Box 1)
    - Sam's Store plastic bag with drawings by Kemnitz (Box 1)
    - Stained glass by Kemnitz, photographed (Box 1)
    - Village Green Apartments, series of paintings for lounge and library 1968 (Box 1)
    - Work for various political and social groups 1967-1985 (Box 1)
  - Publications
    - "About Ann Arbor" magazine, articles and drawings 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - "Ann Arbor Magazine," drawings 1986 (Box 1)
    - "Ann Arbor Now and Then," a book of personal drawings 1972 (Box 1)
    - "Ann Arbor Now and Then," publicity 1972 (Box 1)
    - "Ann Arbor Now and Then," related materials 1972 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Observer, cover drawings 1978-1988 (Box 1)
    - "Ann Arbor Scene Magazine," articles and drawings 1972-1987 (Box 1)
    - "Campustown," in Michigan Alumnus June 1962 (Box 1)
    - "Graphic Works of Milt Kemnitz," Special Issue of "Executive Style," 1978 (Box 1)
    - "London and Back," publicity 1977 (Box 1)
    - "London and Back," correspondence 1977-1983 (Box 1)
    - "Michigan Alumnus," drawings 1967-1985 (Box 1)
    - "Michigan Memento," 1967 (Box 1)
    - "Michigan Memories," 1965 (Box 1)
    - "Michigan School Band and Orchestra Association Journal," cover drawings 1962-1986 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous cover drawings 1973-1985 (Box 2)
    - [cover drawings for] University of Michigan publications 1978-1986 (Box 2)
  - Galleries, Exhibits, Auctions and Art Fairs
    - Ann Arbor Art Association
      - Group exhibit 1954 (Box 2)
      - "Twenty seven years of Milt Kemnitz" exhibit 1974 (Box 2)
      - "Impressions" exhibit 1987 (Box 2)
    - Blixt Gallery, Ann Arbor, exhibits 1982-1984 (Box 2)
    - Catherine McCauley Health Center auction 1980-1987 (Box 2)
    - Children's Leukemia Foundation auction 1981 (Box 2)
    - Detroit Artists Market exhibit 1972 (Box 2)
    - Detroit Institute of Arts exhibit 1956 (Box 2)
    - Drama Lab, Inc. auction 1980 (Box 2)
    - Focus: HOPE auction 1975 (Box 2)
    - Format Gallery, Ann Arbor, exhibit 1988 with photos (Box 2)
    - Forsythe Gallery, Ann Arbor
      - Correspondence and clippings 1957-1980 (Box 2)
      - Group exhibits 1957-1980 (Box 2)
      - "Georgian Bay" exhibit 1957 (Box 2)
      - "Campustown" exhibit 1962 (Box 2)
      - Exhibit 1967 photos (Box 2)
      - Exhibit 1972 with photos (Box 2)
      - "Sesqui Salute!" exhibit 1974 (Box 2)
    - Forum Gallery, Brighton, England 1969-1977 (Box 2)
    - Garelick's Gallery, Detroit, exhibit 1961 with photo of Kemnitz (Box 2)
    - Jacobson's Studio of Fine Arts, Birmingham, Mich., exhibit 1962-1963 (Box 2)
    - Lawrence Institute of Technology, Southfield, Mich., exhibit 1985 (Box 2)
    - Madonna College scholarship dinner auction 1989 (Box 2)
    - Metropolitan Hospital, Detroit, exhibit 1963 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Academy of Science Arts and Letters exhibit 1956 (Box 2)
    - National Maritime Union exhibit, N.Y. 1945 (Box 2)
    - Robert Thom Gallery, "Ships of the Great Lakes," solo exhibit, Birmingham, Mich. 1976 (Box 2)
    - St. Clair Art Fair 1972-1983 (Box 2)
    - Scarab Club "Silver Medal" exhibit 1978 (Box 2)
    - Studio 23 Art Center, Bay City, Mich., exhibit 1979 (Box 2)
    - Thurston Room Art Gallery exhibit 1975 (Box 2)
    - Traverse City Contemporary Art Society and Gallery 1963 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan Hospitals Arts Program exhibit 1987 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan Turner Geriatric Services exhibit 1991 (Box 2)
    - Wauseon Public Library, Wauseon, Ohio, exhibit 1973 (Box 2)
    - Women's American ORT auctions 1975-1977 (Box 2)
- Supplemental materials
  The SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIALS series includes Art Organizations & Associations of which Kemnitz was a member. The chronological Correspondence files are primarily letters to Kemnitz, and many of them relate to his professional life. Miscellaneous Personal Material includes articles about Kemnitz, the folders about the Bird Hills Park controversy, newspaper clippings, personal milestones, and two dismounted scrapbooks documenting his career.
  - Art Organizations and Associations
    - Ann Arbor Art Association 1959-1987 (Box 2)
    - Bloomfield Art Association 1973-1978 (Box 2)
    - Detroit Artists Market 1958-1982 (Box 2)
    - Detroit Institute of Arts, Founders Society 1963-1980 (Box 2)
    - Flint Institute of Arts 1973-1994 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Watercolor Society 1961-1993 (Box 2)
    - Toledo Museum of Art 1973-1989 (Box 2)
    - Washtenaw County Historical Society 1963-1994 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Letters from Waldo and Dottie Grenier 1960-1992 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1941-1976 (Box 2)
      - 1977-1983 (Box 2)
      - 1984-1994 Undated (Box 2)
    - Politicians 1964-1990 (Box 2)
    - Thank yous for charitable donations 1963-1994 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan 1932-1995 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Personal Material
    - Articles about Kemnitz 1978-1992 (Box 2)
    - Bird Hills Park Controversy
      - General undated, 1968-1991, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Clippings 1968-1991, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Milestones
      - Kemnitz honored for fifty year membership at the First Unitarian Universalist Church of Ann Arbor 1987 (Box 3)
      - "Milt Kemnitz Day," 1974 (Box 3)
      - University of Michigan Class of 1933 50th reunion, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Scrapbooks (dismounted)
      - Scrapbook 1, ca. 1980-1984 (Box 3)
      - Scrapbook 2, ca. 1990-1993 (Box 3)
    - Student (U-M) papers (2 expandable folders) (Box 3)
- Southern white migration to Detroit in the 1930s
  The SOUTHERN WHITE MIGRATION TO DETROIT IN THE 1930s series dates mainly from 1936-1937 when Kemnitz, as part of a sociology course at the University of Michigan conducted interviews and made observations on the topic of the adjustment and life of Southern whites who migrated to the industrial North. The files provide some information on church life, the reaction of shop keepers and social agencies to the migrants, their work within the auto plants, and general living conditions. Of note is the information accumulated relating to activities of the Black Legion in Michigan. Some of these files were created by a classmate of Kemnitz, Elmer Akers.
  - Project Files:
    - Case analyses, various tabulations, and data (Box 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Maps, statistical tracts, articles (Box 3)
    - "Labor migration and Social Security" (Outline of purpose and problem) (Box 3)
    - Summaries of individual interviews and related (Box 3)
    - Completed questionnaires (Box 3)
    - Summaries of interviews and observations (with those who interacted with the Southern whites: churches, shop keepers, social agencies; includes some notes on Black Legion members and activities) (Box 3)
  - Seminar reports and research papers
    - Elmer Akers. "A social psychological interpretation of the Black Legion" 1937 (Box 3)
    - Elmer Akers."Southern whites in Detroit" July 1937 (Box 3)
    - Elmer Akers."Southern white migration to the Detroit area" (with Milton Kemnitz) 1937 (Box 3)
    - Southern white migration seminar reports (Box 3)
    - A.H. Hawley seminar paper: "The mobility of Southern immigrant in Detroit" 1937 (Box 3)
      (for Sociology 262, The Metropolitan Community)
  - Related Materials
    - Correspondence with Social Security Board regarding appointment and travel expenses (Box 3)
    - "Emergency relief policies since 1930" (term report for seminar conducted by William Haber) (Box 3)
    - Report before the meeting of Earhart Scholars (Box 3)
    - Unemployment compensation research (Box 3)
    - "An analysis of Detroit purchasing power by districts" (Box 3)